Finding Aid for William Warner Bishop pamphlets and reprints
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Warner Bishop pamphlets and reprints 1900-1951
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.
721 DA 2; B622.8; P186
Reference Librarian at the Library of Congress, 1904-1915 and Librarian of the University of Michigan, 1905-1915. Journal articles and other writings on library topics.
1 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from a variety of sources.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William Warner Bishop was librarian of the University of Michigan from 1915 until his retirement in 1941. After graduating from the University of Michigan (M.A. 1893), Bishop taught Greek at Missouri Wesleyan College (1893-1894) and then became an instructor in New Testament Greek and assistant librarian at Garrett Biblical Institute in Evanston, Illinois. He was a fellow at the American School for Classical Studies in Rome in 1898-1899. On his return to the United States he became librarian and instructor in Latin at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, New York, where he served from 1899 to 1902. Two years as head cataloger at Princeton University preceded his appointment as reference librarian at the Library of Congress in 1904. Bishop remained at the Library of Congress serving from 1907 to 1915 as superintendent of the reading room. In 1915, he was appointed librarian at the University of Michigan, succeeding Theodore Wesley Koch.
As librarian, Bishop was greatly responsible for the growth of the collection, the development and training of the staff, and the contacts established with European bookdealers and librarians. One of Bishop's most significant contributions was the establishment under his leadership of a department of library science to train individuals in bibliographical and other library-related skills.
Bishop was highly respected within his profession. He served as consultant on many of the library projects sponsored by the Carnegie Corporation; and he was chairman of the Advisory Group on College Libraries which assisted in building up the book collections of many college libraries in the United States and Canada. In no area of library work did he make a greater contribution than in international relations. In 1928 Bishop was invited by the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace to head the American group of librarians and others in initiating the reorganization of the Vatican Library. In addition, he served as president of the International Federation of Library Associations from 1931 to 1936; and as chairman of the International Relations Committee of the American Library Association, he promoted exchanges of library personnel and was instrumental in bringing many foreign librarians to this country and in providing library experience abroad for selected American librarians.
Bishop died February 19, 1955.
The William Warner Bishop pamphlets and reprints consists of journal articles and other writings on library topics.
Subjects:
Library of Congress.; Libraries.; Librarianship.
- Pamphlets and reprints.
  - Adult Education-A Challenge to Phi Beta Kappa, School and Society [ April 2, 1927 ] (Box 1)
  - The Advisory Group on College Libraries of the Carnegie Corporation, College and Reference Library Yearbook [ 1931 ] (Box 1)
  - The American College Library and its Librarian. [Claremont library series, no. l June 1932 ] (Box 1)
  - The American Library Association at the Crossroads. [ 1919 ] (Box 1)
  - The American Library Association: Fragments of Autobiography, The Library Quarterly [ January, 1949 ] (Box 1)
  - The American Library Association II: Fragments of Autobiography, The Library Quarterly [ January, 1951 ] (Box 1)
  - American Library Association Study of Adult Education, Proceedings of National University Extension Association [ 1925 ] (Box 1)
  - Die Amerikanischen Bibliotheken. Juli-Dezember 1911 and Janvar-Marz 1912. [Zeitschrift Juni, 1912 ] (Box 1)
  - The Amount of Help to be Given to Readers. Library Journal [Reprint July 1908 ] (Box 1)
  - The Backs of Books [New York Public Library, New York 1914 ] (Box 1)
  - Bericht uber die Amerikanischen Bibliotheken. Janvar bis Juni 1913, Zeitschrift [Dezember 1913 ] (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketches of Librarians and Bibliographers, no. XXVI. Raymond Cagallis Davis, Bulletin of Bibliography and Dramatic Index [ May-August, 1920 ] (Box 1)
  - Books for Teachers in Secondary Schools, Educational Review [New York February, 1900 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - A Call to Service, Michigan Library Bulletin [ August, 1918 ] (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Corporation and College Libraries, 1929-1938. [ 1938 ] (Box 1)
  - Cataloging as an Asset. [ 1916 ] (Box 1)
  - Centralized Purchasing for American College Libraries The Library Quarterly [ October, 1937 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - Changing Ideals in Librarianship, Library Journal [ January, 1919 ] (Box 1)
  - College Days-1889-93, Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review [July 31 1948 ] (Box 1)
  - The College Library and College Teaching, Bulletin of the Association of American Colleges [ May, 1937 ] (Box 1)
  - College Library Standards. [New York 1932 ] (Box 1)
  - Catalogs of printed books, prospectus, 1942 [Congress, Library of [and] Assoc. of Research Libraries. 1942 ] (Box 1)
  - Handbook of the Libraries in the District of Columbia [Congress, Library of [and] Cosmos Club 1914 ] (Box 1)
  - Contribution of the Library to College Teaching, Library Journal, [ March, 1929 ] (Box 1)
  - Cooperation of the University Library. Opportunity for investigation in Natural History by high school teachers. [Ann Arbor 1933 ] (Box 1)
  - A Decade of Library Progress in America, The Popular Science Monthly [ December, 1904 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - The Distribution of Early British-printed Americana in American Libraries, Miscellanea Giovanni Mercati, volume VI, [ 1946 ] (Box 1)
  - Do Children Know the Alphabet?, Education Review [ April, 1902 ] (Box 1)
  - The Eastern Creeds and the Old Roman Symbol The American Journal of Theology [ July, 1902 (Reprint) ] (Box 1)
  - Elements d'Archeologie Chretienne. Par Horace Marucchi., Reviewed by WWB. American Journal of Theology (Box 1)
  - Fashions in Books, Wisconsin Library Bulletin [ June 1922 ] (Box 1)
  - General Discussion. Library Conference, Atlanta University 1941 (Box 1)
  - German Reformation Pamphlets in Princeton University, Princeton University Bulletin [ 1904 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - In Aid of College Libraries, The Library Journal [ May, 1930 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - Incidents in Working on, Short Title Catalog. The Library Quarterly [ July 1950 ] (Box 1)
  - Instructions for Charging Books, [Government Printing Office 1914 ] (Box 1)
  - The Interchange of Librarians. Students and Teachers of Librarianship. Address to World Library Congress, Rome, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Interlibrary Loans, The Library Journal [ December, 1909 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - International Loans Between Libraries 1931 (Box 1)
  - International Relations. American Library Association, Bulletin [ October, 1927 ] (Box 1)
  - International Relations: Fragments of Autobiography, The Library Quarterly [ October, 1949 ] (Box 1)
  - JCM Hanson and International Cataloging., photocopy (Box 1)
  - Judge Woodward and the Catholepistemiad, Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review [ July 28, 1945 ] (Box 1)
  - Junior College Libraries, The Junior College Journal [ December, 1934 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - Junior College Libraries Reprint, The Junior College Journal [ January, 1936 ] (Box 1)
  - Leadership Through Learning [ 1916 ] (Box 1)
  - Libraries and University Extension Adult Education and the Library, [ February, 1926 ] (Box 1)
  - Libraries in the International Picture, ALA Bulletin [ January, 1942 ] (Box 1)
  - The Library and Post-school Education, School and Society [ January 2, 1920 ] (Box 1)
  - The Library of Congress, 1907-15: Fragments of Autobiography, The Library Quarterly [ January, 1948 ] (Box 1)
  - The Library of Congress [GPO 1912 ] (Box 1)
  - The Library of Congress [2nd ed. GPO 1914 ] (Box 1)
  - The Library of Congress [3rd ed. GPO 1922 ] (Box 1)
  - Library of Congress, Preprint of Manual of Library Economy, chapter II. [American Library Association Pub. Board 1911 ] (Box 1)
  - Library Service in the Junior College, The Junior College Journal [ May 1935 ] (Box 1)
  - The Library Service to the University, Michigan Alumnus [May 18 1929 ] (Box 1)
  - The Library's Contribution to Scholarship, The John Crerar Library Quarterly [ 1942 ]
  - El lomo de los libros, Boletin de la comision protectora de bibliotecas populares [Junio-Julio-Augusto 1943 ] (Box 1)
  - The Men Behind the Books. Reprint, The Library Journal [ November, 1931 ] (Box 1)
  - One Problem for 1950--Woodpulp Paper in Books, Bookman's Holiday [N.Y. Public Library 1943 (Reprint)], 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Practical Handbook of Modern Library Cataloging. [Page proof, Waverly Press 1914 ] (Box 1)
  - A Preliminary Checklist of American Copies of Short Title Catalog Books [Ann Arbor April, 1941 ] (Box 1)
  - Princeton: 1902-1907 Fragments of Autobiography, Library Quarterly [ July 1946 ] (Box 1)
  - The Problem for 1950--Woodpulp Paper in Books, Wilson Library Bulletin [ September 1943 ] (Box 1)
  - Rare Book Rooms in Libraries, The Library Quarterly [ July, 1942 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - Recataloging and Reclassification in Large Libraries. American Library Association, Bulletin [ January, 1934 ] (Box 1)
  - The Record of Science, Science [ August 25, 1922 ] (Box 1)
  - Reminiscences of Princeton: 1902-1907, Princeton University Chronicle [ June, 1947 ]
  - Research Libraries in America, Saertrykk av overbibliotekar Wilhelm Munthe [...1933] (Box 1)
  - Resources of American Libraries, The Library Quarterly [ October 1938 ] (Box 1)
  - The Responsibility of American Libraries for the Acquisition of Materials for Research. From: Randall, William M., ed., The Acquisition and Cataloging of Books [ 1940 ] (Box 1)
  - Roman Church Mosaics of the First Nine Centuries. Reprint, American Journal of Archaeology [ 1906 ] (Box 1)
  - Rome and Brooklyn, 1899-1902 Fragments of Autobiography, The Library Quarterly [ October, 1945 ] (Box 1)
  - A Sketch of the History of Learning in Europe: From the Days of Aristotle to the Invention of Printing. Course of Eight Lectures, 190-? (Box 1)
  - Some Chicago Librarians of the Nineties: Fragments of Autobiography, The Library Quarterly [ October 1944 ] (Box 1)
  - Some Library Gains from the War, The Bookman, [ 1918 ?] (Box 1)
  - Some Newer Responsibilities of American Libraries, Zentralblatt fur Bibliothekswesen [ 1933 ] (Box 1)
  - Some Responsibilities of University Library Extension Service. Reprint, Library Journal [ 1923 ] (Box 1)
  - The Status of Library Schools in Universities [ 1933 ], 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Subject Headings in Dictionary Catalogs [ALA conference 1906 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - A Temple of American History: The William L. Clements Library [ 1922 ] (Box 1)
  - The Theory of Reference Work. Bulletin of the ALA [v. 9 (Reprint)] (Box 1)
  - To Directors of Libraries: [Microfilming Project for Pre-1550 Books Printed in English]. Letter April 15,1936 (Box 1)
  - Training in the Use of Books., The Sewanee Review [ July 1912 ] (Box 1)
  - Two Unsolved Problems in Library Work. Reprint, The Library Journal [ January, 1912 ] (Box 1)
  - Union Catalogs. Reprint, The Library Quarterly [ January, 1937 ] (Box 1)
  - University Libraries: Some Reflections on the Dedication of the Sterling Memorial Library at Yale University., The Library Quarterly [ July 1931 ] (Box 1)
  - The University Library's Bookplates, Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review [ August 11, 1951 ] (Box 1)
Related Material
Related collections at the Bentley Historical library include:
William Warner Bishop papers, 1891-1955.
University of Michigan. Library.